We couldn't have got more square in like
the bull's-eye of Microsoft. They turned
the entire company against us.
This is James Everingham, former head of
engineering at Instagram with experience
across many companies including pre-IPO
Netscape. People are going to use the
superior solution, right? Nope.
Microsoft's like, "Watch this. It's not
a technology war, it's a distribution
war." At Instagram, he worked closely
with the CTO and co-founder Mike
Krieger. Mikey brought me in. The
engineering was hitting about 100
people. It's a common place where teams
start to break. He shared many
interesting stories across his 30-year
career. I remember telling my product
partner Kevin Weil at the time, "Hey, I
think I'm going to go do this." And then
like the next day he comes in and goes,
"I think I got to go do this, too."
What? When you look back on your whole
career, is there any career regret?
Yeah, there's a lot, actually.
Here's the full episode.
I kind of got kicked out of college when
I was
uh just starting out when I was 18, but
they hired me 2 weeks later as a
full-time computer scientist. Like
At Netscape? No, this was like early in
my career. Like you know, like I was 18.
I was in college. I didn't go to my
classes. I was just programming my
computer.
Um the library library computer
information uh at Penn State started
using my software that I uploaded.
Um and uh they learned I was local. So,
they they actually had me come in and uh
they wanted me to come in and actually
help them with migrating all their
mainframe stuff to PCs.
Meanwhile, uh the computer science
program I didn't go to any of my
classes, so they kicked me out.
But totally like the left hand not
knowing what the right hand was doing,
like they they were like, "Hey, we want
to offer you a full-time staff
position." And I was like the first
person hired at the university in over
50 years without a degree in a full
staff position.
I had to call up my mom and tell her
this, you know, like
"Hey, I got bad news and good news." And
she start crying, you know, like when
she learned I got kicked out. So, am I
understanding correctly, they they
booted you as a student and then they
hired you as a full-time They full-time
kicked me out. They sent me a letter
saying, "You need to re-evaluate your
educational goals. You can reapply
later." But like you I literally got a
0.0.
Oh my god. I literally didn't go to any
of my classes. Like I was just
programming at home and uh
totally, you know, um was was was
working on this software that I was like
obsessed with. I was all night working
and I was uploading it. It was open
source at the time. It was called
shareware.
And um
the university just randomly got a hold
of it and was using it. And they were
like, "This guy's local. Let's Let's get
him in. We don't have anyone with this
ex-
expertise." So, I end up working for the
university for years.
That's so interesting. When you When you
got booted and hired at the same time,
was that positive like a net positive
for you or is that Oh, unbelievably so.
It was like, you know, I basically was
able to go and like I I did was
interested in learning. So, like I ended
up taking pretty much all the computer
science classes that the university had
over the next few years. And And I never
got a degree because I never took any of
the electives, but I I had like 150
credits of like advanced comp sci cuz I
took them for free. I was staff. I could
just go take They couldn't even argue
with me. They couldn't even say like you
can't go into this class. Some of them
were honors classes and you had to be an
honor student or staff.
You didn't get the degree, but you got
the education. I did. I It was more of a
yeah, I I I did, but I I can't say that
I learned the most from school.
It was more from, you know,
uh
from from from going off and like
pursuing like my software the you know,
my my curiosity outside of the
university because, you know, I worked
there for 2 years and people started
kept sending me money for this like open
source software. So, I'm like, "I'm
going to quit and start my own company
and just go do that."
So, uh I did that. You know, I left
university and started my first company
when I was 20.
You said open source, and in my mind,
that's GitHub. Oh, yeah. No. That This
was a very different world back in the
early '80s. This was like you write
code, and you would use a modem, and
you'd connect to a bulletin board, and
you'd upload your code. And it was
called shareware, freeware at the time.
Um and then people would go on these
bulletin boards. It was like, you know,
one user per bulletin board. You had to
sit there and redial until you get
get your chance to connect, and
and you could browse, you know, it was
like I'm talking like 1,200 baud, you
know, like you can almost read the
characters. And then you'd find the
file, and then it would take, you know,
sometimes a half a day to download.
Yeah, I mean, a very different time.
I see. Okay, so you you would connect to
some shared server that was horrendously
slow.
It wasn't even shared. It was like
bulletin boards were sort of these like
um uh you know, I ran one, too. So, it
was like uh
this this system that was running on
someone's computer in their house um
with a single modem and a single phone
line on it, and you would connect to
this, and then you could use it.
And then the way these can like the If
you wanted to send a message, some of
these were like networks.
And um the way they would work is they
would all shut down at like 1:00 in the
morning and start calling each other and
syncing their messages. And so, like
there was like a few hours a night where
they were just doing that.
This was like early. This was like wild
west.
Yeah, I mean, I can just imagine all of
the security potential security
vulnerabilities from Oh, well, it was a
whole different time. Yeah, of course.
Yeah, it was It was Security wasn't a
thing back then, and you know, like that
was I was a hacker, right? That's how I
got into it, too, is I was writing
software that would take over the phone
systems. I was a teenager, the FBI
showed up at my house and
asked me to stop.
How did they find you?
They traced my number. I was like a kid.
Oh, there's two things. Um one, they
traced my number, but the other thing
was I wrote hacking software and uh
I was like
16 when I wrote this and I was proud of
my software and so I put my name on it.
Okay. Okay, that's how they found you.
You can go still search the internet and
you'll find it. So.
>> What did it do? It allowed you to
completely take over an operator's phone
line. Like you could uh
you could blow using frequencies. At the
time it was called freaking and like I
had a Commodore and the Commodore had
this like multi-sound chip. So, you
could generate two tones at once and you
could basically call and blast 2600
hertz into an operator line if they were
on the right system and it would
literally blow her off the line.
And then the keypads generated different
tones than a regular touch tone. So, you
had to have those and there were a
couple extra keys, KP and ST. So, you
had to have these extra keys and know
then the sequences.
My software emulated all those
frequencies, did the 2600 tone and then
had stuff built into it to
allow you to do anything an operator
would do. Like you want to listen in on
somebody's conversation, you could do
that. You could do free phone calls.
When the FBI showed up on your doorstep,
is that uh who answered the door? Is
that you or your parents?
Okay.
Did she know what was going on? Well, um
she knew it was for me and she so, you
know, I was concerned. Like, you know,
she was the
She didn't understand what a computer
was. Like, I didn't either at the time
to be honest. I thought I was wasting my
life and she was like that.
You're down on that video game. You're
not doing your schoolwork. I was like,
oh, well. No, I did not know she was
wrong. So, At the beginning of your
career something stood out to me. I saw
Netscape and I know Netscape is super
famous for
the first iteration of the browser wars.
And I was curious because you joined so
early, what's the story behind you
joining and what was it like at the
time?
Like it sort of goes back to like how I
got to California in the first place. It
was like I um there was a company called
Borland back in the day that was
it was sort of like where all the good
engineers were in the valley and they
wrote Borland C++ and Turbo Pascal. They
were a languages company. They were
being um
um they were probably the main
competitor back in the early 90s uh to
Microsoft. And uh
I learned on Borland tools. So,
you know, I got a call because of my
open source software that I had. They
had seen that I was building developer
tools. So, they
they recruited me to come out and
interview. I didn't think they'd hire
me, but they did.
And um
uh
so, I went in there and uh I worked
there for years. And uh when Netscape
when Netscape uh first came on my radar,
uh it was through Borland some Borland
colleagues that went over.
Um mainly my close friend Lloyd Tab who
went on to found Looker.
Uh and uh
he recruited me over and you know, it
was probably
it was probably like some of the worst
judgment that worked out for the
positive for me ever because
Micro- Microsoft was just beating
beating us up bad at at Borland. Like
they were, you know, Visual Studio came
out and like they were competing with
everything and we were just losing
market share.
Layoff after layoff and I'm like, I got
to go get out of Microsoft's way. Like I
I I'll go join this little internet
startup. You know, Microsoft wants
nothing to do with that.
Turns out that was pretty
that was wrong.
Like we got
We kind of got square more square in
like the bullseye of Microsoft. They
turned the entire company against us,
right? Like they
they were they were off, you know,
building
building the browser into the operating
system and all these things that were
just almost impossible to compete with
and it ends up being a pretty intense
time.
But it was Borland, you know, like one
of the things I think that's interesting
about
my career and I think it's a good
pattern for others is like you end up
building great relationships with people
and companies.
And
that opens up doors and creates
opportunity for you
later in your career. So
Borland, you know, building great
relationships there took me to
Netscape which
honestly even my current company Guild
that I have three people that have been
on along that journey all the way since
Netscape with me and we've done five,
six companies together.
Wow, six companies.
Yeah, I think when you're like kind of
going through your career, a lot of
people
they give you that advice. They say,
yeah, you should network or you should
kind of but
and the immediate action I am is like,
oh, do I do I start talking to people?
Do I start I don't know do coffee chats?
I don't know exactly what.
But if you were to sum up your
understanding of what good networking is
for someone who's in tech, what what
does that look like? Yeah, I you know,
it looks different now to me than than
than when I was younger and I wish I I
had this filter when I was younger but
like
one
I think people that ask a lot of
questions going in and are curious. It's
a great way to build relationships in a
in a company.
When you're first starting out your
career and I was the same as like I
wanted good mentors around me.
And
my my my good buddy Lloyd who I already
mentioned, like he has the best advice
and it's like look, if you want to find
a mentor, don't go and ask someone,
"Hey, I need a mentor."
Go offer them help. Like, "Hey, you
know,
how can I help you?" And it will
naturally
evolve into a good mentorship for you.
Like so,
try to be useful to others, be curious
about others' work.
Don't be afraid to speak up in meetings.
Like just start
just start talking and listening. And um
I think that it's important to build
this network and uh
or at least, you know, don't don't make
enemies, right? It's like I think that
there was a
quote, I can't remember who said it. It
might have been Bill Gates, but he might
have been re-quoting as like, you know,
friends come and go, but enemies
collect.
And you know, I think that's something
to that. Like, you know,
build good relationships and don't burn
bridges, you know, I remember sitting at
Netscape
the the people sitting around me, like
even, you know, John Giannandrea sitting
right next to me building the plug-in
interface.
He now reports to Tim Cook running all
AI at Apple and you know, he ran all
search at Google.
And you know, the next person, you know,
my my first one of my first college
hires went on to found a company and
sold it for 400 million a few years
later. Like
the people that you're sitting next to
are going to look a lot different in 20
years.
You mentioned Netscape and I was in my
research I saw that the company went
from just starting to IPO in 16 months
and in today's market, I feel like
companies wait a lot longer for for IPO.
What was it like at the time and why did
it IPO so quickly?
That was a crazy ride. Like first off,
the
the rapid scaling was insanity even by
any standards today. I think when I
started there, you know, there was about
150 people total. Um, but that the
engineering team was incredibly small
compared to that. It was not um,
majority engineering at that point. Um,
I think within a year we were over 3,000
people.
Within a year? Yeah.
So, I I worked 7 days a week and like
there was a time where I took 2 days off
and I came back in and there were people
sitting around me I had no idea who they
were. I'm like
It was just like a a parade of people
coming in sitting it was complete chaos.
So, uh
Yeah, so that went very quick. But like
on the IPO question, um, I believe that
was September 9th it was like sort of a
day that sticks in my head of 1995.
I was there pre-IPO.
Uh
looking forward like there are a lot of
it was a lot of less regulation back
then, you know, you didn't have
Sarbanes-Oxley or any of these things
that like would prevent you from going
public.
It was a way to raise more capital. Um,
if you had a good story you could go
out. I mean, there was a crazy stream of
like the dot com bubble is crazy IPO
after IPO, right? Like
and
everyone was just
buying stock that was a web company.
They didn't care what it was because
they wanted to get in for the IPO and
a lot of people didn't do well with
that, you know, if you bought Webvan or
you know, one of these I even saw I even
saw a company that was formed to to ship
potatoes. Like it was like potatoes
direct or something. It's like, wait,
you're you're going to charge 100 bucks
to FedEx a bag of potatoes. That's your
business?
But people were like investing in this
stuff and um
so they they decided to come in and put
some regulation around that.
Which was a good thing.
So, you know, now and the competition
there's a lot more companies out there
competing and people know that you need
to have
real revenue. You need to be able to
predict what that is going to look like
in a year. You have to show steady
growth. So,
that's evolved into a space that is a
little more organized, a little more
governed, and a little more sane these
days.
You You mentioned that you you left your
previous company to get away from the
competition with Microsoft and and then
I understand
that Netscape's like one of the most
famous competitors with early Microsoft.
And I want to know like when you got to
Netscape, at what point were you
realizing, "Oh, crap, we're competing
with Microsoft." It was pretty quick.
Like we got in there and suddenly, you
know, Microsoft put out this um big
like
uh communication saying like this is
next essential threat. You know, they
looked at us like an operating system
and people were going to start using web
applications instead of shrink-wrapped,
you know, operating systems and uh
software that they sold.
Um you know, interestingly though, uh
it ended up
the the thing that they were afraid of
ended up actually making them one of the
biggest companies in the world cuz it
expanded like they adapted well, it
expanded uh the market so dramatically
that they, you know, they were able to
offer services, reinvent, and do all
that stuff. But it came pretty quick and
uh you know, our mistake was my big
mistake, a big learning uh for me was uh
I was um
working on this browser and I kept
thinking like, "Look, um
we're going to build a better browser.
The technology's superior." And it was
for a long time. It was like and it was
like so people were going to use a
superior solution, right? Nope.
Microsoft's like, "Watch this. It's not
a technology war, it's a distribution
war. And we're going to just bundle this
and give it away
and people will
not use your stuff anymore. And that's
literally what happened, right? Like
people didn't didn't care once
especially when like the quality became
pretty equal, right? Like if you have
two products that the quality is pretty
equal, people are going to just use the
one that's the default. There's no
reason to switch.
And that's how Netscape made money. We
sold these browsers, right? That was our
original model. Like we sold these they
were like 35 bucks. We were growing
fast.
And then the Microsoft gave it away and
instantly killed all the revenue going
to Netscape uh for the browsers.
What was the the internal reaction at
Netscape among you and your peers when
the competition was happening? At first
like we felt like we were on a mission.
Like the engineers, we felt like we were
on uh like this mission of
interconnecting the world and bringing
it. So like we were really focused on
that. So on one way it was validating.
Like oh, you know, this is a big space.
Microsoft sees it. But on the other hand
it was like completely depressing and
stressful. It's like okay, they just
gave away our product. What do we do?
Um
Uh luckily, you know, we had
the Netscape browser would default to
netscape.com. That was like the
landing page and we had a tremendous
amount of traffic. So we started
monetizing netscape.com as the first
like web service and added like email to
it. Like webmail and things like that.
And so that started actually filling
that gap.
But we had to invent that on the fly and
it was a stressful time to get there.
I I was reading the Wikipedia page about
the browser wars and I saw like a really
interesting part about the competition.
It said in 1997
September they launched Internet
Explorer 4.
And on the release
they they put a a giant E logo somewhere
in San Francisco and it says Netscape
employees showing up to work the
following morning found the logo on the
front lawn paired with a greeting card
signed best wishes the IE team. Did Did
you work in that office and see that
that happen?
>> was little that was in San Francisco.
They put that on the front lawn of our
office, the one I was in. So uh
So yeah, they went and put this big I
mean it was
it was friendly competition in one way.
Like you know, because the Valley
engineers move around. So there was a
bunch of my Borland colleagues were at
Microsoft and
there was some friendly rivalry, but
like you know
it was interesting that they did that
and I actually know exactly the person
who did that.
And um um yeah, I believe that was Hody
Partovi and uh
when I went to after Netscape, I went to
Tellme Networks. Hody and I were uh you
know, I worked with Hody directly. Like
he we we were both running parts of
engineering. Um I actually reported in
initially to Hody and we would just
basically tell stories about like yeah,
we were doing this and he was like and
he was running IE. So and I was running
the Netscape browser. So we got to tell
these these stories back and forth.
Yeah, so the I guess the story goes is I
mean the superior technology didn't work
for Netscape and the distri-
distribution advantage that Microsoft
had was too much and so ultimately
Microsoft ended up winning. I saw that
Mozilla was created because Netscape
just gave away the technology, gave away
the browser. Why would Netscape choose
to give the source code away?
Sure, it was a bold move at the time and
I believe the person who originally
suggested it was Jamie Zawinski and uh
um and uh also known as JWZ and like
he's he's pretty well known out there,
but
Um so here was the thing. We were
out-resourced. We were a small company
compared to Microsoft. You know, we had
dozens of engineers working on the
browser. They had thousands. Like, you
know, it was very hard to compete.
So we're like, how do we completely
change the game? And like, why don't we
invite the world to help us? Like, we're
on this righteous mission to like um
open to to to make inner you know, the
make people connected and share
information. So why don't we give away
the browser? Let's let's give it away.
Let's open source it and invite the
world to come in and help. That was the
only way we could see of engaging
thousands of developers to to come help.
And uh
it was a lot of work to get there,
right? And and it did work, right? Like
Mozilla became the foundation and of
lots of components that had made it into
Chrome and there was Firefox and you
know, still going strong. So uh you
know, in one way that did work.
But it was hard getting there. Like the
story is even open sourcing the code. Uh
I mean, we had You couldn't even like
distribute SSL source code back then. It
was like deemed a munition by the
government. So we had to
not only remove SSL from the open source
version, we couldn't even like show how
the APIs would work. So we had to
obfuscate APIs.
And then we were a bunch of, you know,
young idiots working on the source code.
So we had like swear words in it and
like inappropriate variable names. So we
had to like print out all the code and
go through it with like highlighters and
like censor our own code.
Uh why didn't you just grep the code for
bad words? Because you don't know what
they are. If you have a
a variable named GG net lib breeding
like bunnies, like how do you grep for
that?
Literally, that was a variable name.
So
So like we had to go through and and and
make sure like it was something that
wasn't going to get us trouble sharing.
Funny story, I think JW's, Jamie, um he
saved all the censored code and then he
released it all. So, like it's you can
go out there and find all of the
censored code from from that.
Oh, that's funny. What You You mentioned
the government deemed SSL um
like a munition. What does that mean? It
meant that it was like um
uh a uh
a dangerous technology. Like if people
could encrypt stuff and and uh and they
and and the government or or, you know,
legal authorities couldn't ever encrypt
it. So, back then
even like very small levels of
encryption were concerning.
And we couldn't distribute it because
like people could weaponize it if they
got a hold of it. That was the theory.
And before we leave this part of your
career, is there any any like um
I I guess lesson learned or, you know,
favorite other story that you'd want to
share? Otherwise, we can go on. Um you
know, I think the lessons learned there
is like when you're joining When you're
joining a company, like understand what
what the actual Who the competition is
and what the war is. You know, I think
that's interesting, especially today,
right? Like
everyone's fighting to win the AI wars.
Like what does that mean? And what is
the war? Is it a technology war? Is it a
data war? Is it a distribution war? Like
what is it?
You know, maybe maybe maybe maybe maybe
uh back into like uh
your career choices from that level of
understanding. If I'm understanding
correctly, you're saying like as an
engineer even, you should be thinking
almost like an investor, like where
which company you go to because
there's much more outside of the
technology. That's right. Think about
it. I think that's a good way to look at
it is like, you know, look if, you know,
when we're young, we probably don't have
a lot of funds to start going investing
in in company.
So, we invest with our time. You know,
we get stock often as a compensation,
you know, for our time. So, like look
look at your portfolio and see where
you're overweighted and you know, if if
if that's your goal,
um
you know, I think that's a a reasonable
way to look at it. Later in your career,
I saw that you joined Instagram.
Actually, when I I worked at Instagram
in the past, you were the head of
engineering when I joined as a new grad.
And um yeah, I kind of wanted
to ask a little bit about that. So, how
did you get hired there? Was it based
off your network like you're saying or
did you go through some other process?
Well, this is a great example of um
of sort of failure leading you to a
place that's better, right? So, like I
went and I I founded a company called
Luminate. And Luminate I worked at for 6
and 1/2 years and basically it was
Instagram shopping, by the way. It was
It was that product but for publisher
sites and we
we worked a long time and we couldn't
get it working. Now, one of my board
members was this
was Elliot Shrag.
Elliot reported to
I believe to Sheryl at the time and
and he was on my board.
When I sold the company, I sold it to
Yahoo. And
but Instagram actually tried to buy it.
So, I met, you know, Emily White and
Mike Krieger and stuff briefly.
Um I committed to only 1 year at Yahoo.
I had I was very good friends with the
chairman of the board
and so he convinced me to go there and
help. And uh
1 year came up and Elliot actually uh
reached out and said, "Hey, Instagram
still looking? Would you please just
come and talk?"
And he didn't know it but like I had
been talking to other companies and I
had verbally accepted a pretty large
position. And uh
but I had to go I had to go I had to go
meet just because it was Elliot and he
wanted me to talk. And then when I So I
went in and I met
Mike Mikey again and
some of the other
people and I'm like, "Oh,
this is the job I want. This is like
this is the call like the values were
clear.
I was passionate. I realized I use the
product. I'm like, "I actually use
Instagram." The company I was almost
going to go to I don't even use.
I think at the end of the process I
probably would have paid to take that
job, but I wasn't going to tell them
that, but it was a job I really wanted.
So uh
So it was my network.
It was the timing. It was like my
previous company that I couldn't make
run that like ran out the runway to make
that timing perfect for me.
It was my experience working on image
stuff at the previous company that sort
of was also helpful.
When when I think about an employee in
big tech,
oftentimes when people consider starting
their own company,
the thinking is either that company's
going to succeed and obviously that's
great, or the company will maybe not do
so hot and I'll just come back to where
I was. But it seems like I've seen in
other many careers, it seems like yours
as well, that even if it's not a
incredible IPO success, there's this
middle ground where companies get
acquired and then you can come in at
very high roles. Like someone might have
left uh I guess the the the big tech
companies at like maybe a middle role or
something like that. They start their
company, it goes not good enough for a
breakout success, but they're a leader
at that company and they get you know,
hired back in at like a senior
leadership position big tech. And I was
curious, what's the the mechanism for
the like the level that you come in at
when you enter back after starting your
own thing? So there's a lot of those,
but like you can't I mean if people
aren't going to bring you in at a senior
level unless you can back it up, unless
you can show your experience. Uh even
though I came from a smaller startup and
uh and went into Yahoo and I went from
15 engineers to 1,200
or something.
Um I had previously ran large
organizations, you know, at Netscape and
you know, Tellme was even pretty large.
So, I had that background already.
I interviewed Ryan Olson. He's one of
the
>> original I know Ryan well. Okay, great.
Yeah. And so, we were talking about
Instagram stories and he mentioned
something really interesting in that
project, which was that actually when
the project started
you immediately kind of cut the size of
the team almost in half or significantly
just down to like Ryan Olson and a few
other people so that the the project
could move faster. And he said that was
a big part of the project's success.
And you were the head of engineering at
the time, so I was curious if you had
any thoughts on
what did you see that that made that a
good decision at the time?
You know, Instagram stories was
an interesting thing. Now, like your
natural instinct is like, hey,
Snapchat's
gaining traction and like we need to go
do what Microsoft did, turn the whole
company against this. But really, this
is where your entrepreneurial skills
come in. It's like, hey,
what we need is a small team that can
move really fast. So, like you want to
set it up so that uh
you have really capable people, you have
the right types of engineers who are
very proactive and then you remove any
roadblocks from them. So, you give them
a separate you give them a separate uh
area where that's not dependent upon
like, you know,
uh
deep deep APIs and blocking points into
other organizations.
So, you set it up so that they can move
fast. And uh that if that's
So, we did that purposely, right? And I
think it was like 3 months we had
It was a 3-month project. We went from
zero to releasing stories, you know, and
it was a pretty big success.
Well, I think maybe a lot of
managers might naively think, oh,
competitor's coming, we got to move
fast. That means throw a lot of
engineering resources at it. So here's
here's a 20-person team. Go, go, go. As
opposed to it sounds like you have
different philosophy here, which is a
few
a small talent dense team.
That's right. With with founders leading
it directly, right? You know, Kevin and
Mikey were heavily involved and you
know,
brilliant product thinking and execution
at that level as well.
You know, when you get you get a small
team that's capable and you give them
clear ownership and you remove
dependencies,
that is one way to increase speed. So if
you get a large team, they tend to be
interdependent. You start federating
large pieces of architecture and pretty
soon,
you know, those dependencies end up
slowing you down.
So I think
the small if you sometimes it's better
to start with something small and build
on it rather than trying to build the
big thing at the beginning and uh
evolve it over time. And that's sort of
what this was. It's like let's get it
working, let's get it stood up, let's
get this thing
working and then plug it into the
product and we'll scale it instead of
like
what does this look like at large scale
and let's build that from assuming that.
That that ends up often being a way less
efficient way to get something done and
it's definitely a lot slower. Mikey
Krieger had like and it was the name of
my conference room.
It was called this value that he said do
the simple thing first. I don't know if
you recall this, but like
hey, you know, like if we're going to go
off and we have a thesis, like before we
go off and just
pour the whole company in it, what's
like the simplest, hackiest thing we can
do to go prove this thesis is true?
And you know, that was sort of part of
the value so that of Instagram is like
what is what's the simplest thing we can
do to go prove this thesis before we
scale it. You were hired as the the head
of engineering and at the time Mike
Krieger was still the the CTO there.
What are the differences between that
CTO role and the head of engineering
role and how did you partner with Mike
Krieger and what what went well, what
didn't?
Yeah, so Mike Mikey brought me in about
the engineering was hitting about 100
people. It's a common place where teams
start to break and uh
Mikey's brilliant. He was actually a
really gifted manager, too, but he just
didn't want to do that and uh he wanted
to focus on the technology and and even
coding. That was his true enjoy. So, he
brought me in.
He was So, the initial
confusing things to the team was like
what are our different roles? Like, you
know, what
who do I listen to? I'm used to getting
directions from Mikey.
So, you have to be pretty clear. So, the
first thing that we did is like we wrote
our job descriptions and we published
them to the org. And so, you know, and
classically a CTO is like works with
customers, um new technologies, uh works
on the product the the technology road
map,
um experiments, all of these things.
Builds the external engineering brand.
And the VP or the head of engineering is
usually people management thing. It's
like
hiring, um
execution, um
org structure, you know, performance
reviews, all that fun stuff, right? And
so,
think technology, uh
road map for CTO, think process, people,
staffing, execution with a VP of Eng.
So, we published that. And we even came
up with like flowcharts. Like, "Hey, I
want to I want you know, we we put it
out to the team. We're like, "Hey, I
want to I want five more head count go
do this project." And it's like, come to
me.
"Hey, you know, I want to use this new
technology. I think it would be cool."
Go to Mikey. So, like we we also put
like a roadmap out there. And then it
took some evangelism. You know, like
you know, to to get get people to learn
where to go for what they needed. People
often confuse this by the way, you know,
it's like people confuse the difference
between a CTO and a VP of Eng. Like, I
get called into a lot of companies
saying, "Hey, we need a new CTO." And
I'm like, "Why? What's breaking?" And
they almost always describe VP of Eng
problems. I'm like,
I don't think you need a CTO. I think
you need a VP of Eng.
It's a very different person.
As we kind of wrap up this Instagram leg
of your career, is there anything that
you think I might have missed or kind of
like lessons that you learned from this
part of your career?
Yeah, no, you know I I I think that the
one thing that I remember is like, you
know, when I came into Instagram,
it was a different company. Everyone's
nervous when they go into a new job and
they brought me in right when
engineering teams start to break, but
like these weren't breaking and I was
very confused at the beginning and I was
starting to feel like I was a dinosaur.
I'm like,
"Wait, you know, this is all working.
This isn't breaking. Like, what kind of
management voodoo is going on here that
I don't understand?" And then about 150
to 200 engineers, it started breaking.
And I'm like, "Oh, wait. They're These
people are so smart. They're able to IQ
their way past like that normal
barrier." Cuz what usually breaks is
communication lines. Like, uh
you have to hold a lot of the stuff in
your head. Use face familiarity with
people. It's called, you know, Dunbar's
number. All that stuff. But like the
people were just so gifted and smart at
Instagram,
um they were able to IQ past that. Plus,
the great thing that reinforcing thing
about Instagram was the best software is
built by people who use it. And like
everyone in Instagram was a power user,
right? Like and
even if you go back to Boomerang, do you
know do you remember Boomerang? Uh when
it first came about, it was
I think it was uh an intern, Tim
Leonardo I think was the intern. He went
and built it as a hackathon in like 3
days.
Like one of the most engaging features
the Instagram released was a hackathon
built by an intern in 3 days. Like it's
just amazing to work in a team where
you're the primary customer and you're
building stuff for yourself. So, anytime
you can do that, like that's awesome.
Moving to the next part of your career,
I saw you I remember when I joined
Instagram, all these very high-profile
people were leaving Instagram to work on
Novi. It was the hot hot project at the
time. I was thinking, oh wow, this this
new crypto thing must be really big. And
so, yeah, what drew you to working on
Novi or the crypto project at at Meta?
And what was the impact you saw in it?
So, inside Meta I had met David Marcus.
David was running um Messenger at the
time.
And
we had just met, but he's like, "Hey, I
want to I want to run something by you."
And I went and he was like,
"Don't tell anyone, but I'm going to
leave Messenger and this is what I'm
going to do." And this is my first
meeting with David. And he's like, "I've
heard good things about you. Um would
would you consider coming and running
the engineering aspect of this? And um
he was selling me this
crazy crypto story." Like and I loved
Instagram, right? And uh
I was like, "You're insane. Like that's
the crazy thing. Why would I
go join that?" And like
I just couldn't get it out of my head.
And then like the next day it started
hitting me like, oh, wait, this is an
area for impact. And uh
so I went back the next day and David
was kind of grinning and he was like, I
knew you'd be back. And he's like he
called it he's like, I call this the
mental virus. He goes it takes about 24
hours for it to infect people and then
they get it. And
I was like, darn you David. And uh long
story short, I'm like, okay, I'm going
to come start this.
I was heavily invested in the mission,
which was um
financial inclusion and uh bringing
bringing safety and low-cost money
movement to people around the world that
needed it. And um
I loved that idea. And uh
I remember telling my product partner
Kevin Weil at the time if
uh
hey, I think I'm going to go do this.
And he's he I explained it to him and he
was kind of like
had that same look I had.
And then like the next day he throws a
30-minute meeting on my calendar and I'm
like, oh, he's going to try and talk me
out of this. And he comes in and goes, I
think I got to go do this, too.
What?
I go, this is going to be tricky. So I
connected him with David and I'm like,
great. Uh this is going to be a tricky
one to navigate. Um but it worked out
well and you know, we went over and
started the Libra project at the time.
How did the project go and you know,
what were the pivotal points in it? Oh
man, I think it's pretty public how that
project went. Like we uh we weren't able
to ship it, right? Like it was uh
there was a lot of pressure on on
Facebook at the time, just politic
political and regulatory and like they
weren't excited about us what their view
was as thinking we're going to rewrite
currency. It's like not what we were
doing, but like there was not a lot of
strong understanding on the government.
They're not the best deepest
technologists. So uh but they didn't
want us to release this and it was a
shame.
David tried to do this like
the right thing. He's like he we we
announced what we were going to do that
we were going to work with regulators
and everything. In retrospect, we
probably should have just released it
and asked for forgiveness.
But that sort of put us into a tailspin
where we had to keep re-architecting the
project to be regulatory compliant.
And took us years to do that. Um and
ultimately
we got it to the point where even the
government said this is the the platinum
version of stablecoin. And uh
but they still didn't want us to release
it. And I think that's when we gave up
and uh
Um we were pretty big org by then. I
think we're like 3,500 people.
And
yeah, they put all payments and
everything under under David at that
point and uh
uh
I think in a funny moment David came to
me. Uh well, I I'm like I can't keep
doing this. I'm going to go do something
different. And I I love David and you
know, very felt like he was a friend. I
didn't want to let him down.
So I took me a couple of weeks to get
the courage up and practice my
resignation to him.
And I was ready. And I'm like I'm going
to go in our one-on-one. Here's my
story. I'm going to give him all the
time but tell him I need to move on.
And I go in there and he and I sit down
and David goes, "Well, before we get
into whatever you want to get into, I
have some news to share with you." I'm
like, "What?" And he's like, "I'm going
to leave." What?
I thought I was going to tell you. And
I'm like, "Well, what are you going to
do?" And he's like, "Nah, I think I'm
going to go get into my entrepreneurial
roots." I'm like, "How?" And like one
thing led to another. We kept talking
and I end up leaving Meta for a couple
of years.
And I went and started Lightspeed Arc
with David cuz I was invested in this
mission of And that's what Lightspeed
Arc's doing and I love it. It's just an
amazing mission of like
Um you know, the way I think about it is
finance is the last area for disruption,
you know, but I do think like the cost
and latency of moving value globally
needs to go to zero cuz when it does
that
when you can move money like packets of
information like you can stream money,
you can move it low cost areas that need
it. Like it's just going to be a
revolution. I've no doubt that that's
going to happen at some point. And so
you were working in the crypto space and
now you're working in AI.
What
are what made you leave the crypto space
if you know there's impact there? Yeah,
first off, you know, I'm like a crypto
skeptic. I never was a buyer into all of
this stuff, but I do think that there
it's really good for money movement and
like as a base layer.
Um
so what happened there was like I was
working and I co-founded Lightspark and
David wanted to do it in LA. So I
figured I'd move down there.
I commuted for 2 years down there and uh
and I formed a team and built it and I
was kind of like at a point where the
team was formed. I'm commuting 3 days a
week. I didn't feel like I was adding a
lot of value until we were at the next
level of scaling.
So I talked to David and you know, David
and I agreed like hey, yeah, fine. I'll
step back and uh
um you know, we're we're we're very good
friends. So it was like uh an easy
conversation. Um I groomed a successor
and and stepped back and at that time
Meta learned I was free
and they were like, hey, you know, we
have a role we want to run by you. We
hear we're here you're free and I'm
like, I don't know what I would
what what that role would be that I'd be
interested in.
And they're like, well, what about dev
infra, you know, like running all the
developer infrastructure at Meta? And
I'm like, oh, hold on. Like
I'm that's my background. Like I'm a
developer tools person. That was the
first 10 years of my career. Like and it
hit me like
oh, wait, you know, what was I even
doing at Instagram and all these things?
I'm a developer tools person. Like
that's really what I want to do and uh
with AI coming into the picture, it was
like
awesome. We get to go write science
fiction stories about how developer
productivity is going to be and go try
to make that happen with unlimited
resources. I'm like sign me up for that.
So, I would so I came back and uh I
loved that team. Dev Infra is amazing
and such a senior team like a thousand
engineers
building all of the developer tooling
for inside Meta. It was just amazing. I
loved that job. Did it for almost two
years.
And um the only reason I left is because
I had that observation and I I had to go
start this company. Like And what was
that observation?
Well, so, you know, we built something
internal called Dev Mate.
Um Dev Mate was an agentic
platform that allowed engineers to sort
of like go learn from each other and
then scale
uh these agents and these agents were
working on tooling, not just coding.
They were driving tools and doing all
types of things.
And it went viral internally. Like um
uh we couldn't keep up with the demand.
Like it within months, like
it needed an entire dev server per Dev
Mate instance and there are 40,000 plus
engineers at Meta and pretty soon
everybody wanted one an instance and
some of them wanted three instances.
So, you're like how do we allocate all
these dev servers?
But it was such strong pull. You're
like, oh,
I see the dynamics at work here. Like
40,000 developers is fun, but it'd be
fun to go do this for 40 million. And uh
so, while we so we took a lot of these
lessons and we're like, yeah, we kind of
think we see around the corner of what
the world needs for this to work inside
their companies and that led to the
formation of Guild. When I look at the
AI space, it it feels like a bloodbath.
There's like incredibly competitive.
When you saw the space, I guess what
what gives you the confidence that you
will compete well or you know, what is
the niche that you're going to focus on?
First off, I don't have the confidence,
but I have the drive. And I'll tell you
that much. Like it's like I I believe I
deeply believe that what we are building
is needed.
Um so there's that. But like I'm always,
you know,
I'm always looking out of the corners of
my eyes of like who else is building
this and you know, who might not
execute. That's just what an
entrepreneur does.
So if you look at a lot of the startups
and a lot of the companies, you know, I
think a lot of them are building for
like the future past. And what I mean by
that is they're building for things that
fill in gaps of what LLMs will probably
be able to do.
Like look at Cursor. It's auto complete.
Now, you know, LLMs are starting to get
to be able to completely write code
without an IDE. It's like, okay, you
wrote you built a product on a bus stop,
not where the end of the line is, you
know. So what's that end of the line and
like what is needed
regardless of all of that.
So what we're building is a control
plane and it's a it's a layer of
infrastructure that allows you to manage
these agents inside a company. Like you
know, your agents if they're rolling
around in your infrastructure, you want
to treat them like employees, right?
Like some of them they they'll some of
them you want to have access to things,
some you want to restrict, you want to
report on what they're doing, you need
to observe, a lot of
you don't want one agent just like
tanking your token budget. You need
circuit breakers. You need a governance
layer for that. Regardless of like where
this ends
or which model company wins,
you need this, right? So like we believe
that we're building, you know, something
that's needed. And
in any like
scenario where Anthropic or OpenAI or
Meta or somebody else wins, you just
need this layer.
Let me paint you a vision of where I
think like things are going to go, okay?
So, I think a few years, like right now
inside the company, you have a bunch of
internal web applications, you have your
HRIS systems and, you know, your
intranets and like developer like CICD
tools and you know, you have a lot of
internal apps.
Think there's going to be a layer of
like thousands of agents that will sit
on top of this and help drive them,
right? For example, you know, we build
an agent that we use on our own system
here that
basically doesn't make duplicate bugs
possible, right? It's really simple
thing. It's like you submit a get issue,
you know, it fires a webhook, our agent
wakes up and goes, "Let me look and see
if there's one that's like this." And it
just marks a duplicate and goes back to
sleep.
That's different than a coding agent,
right? So, uh
you can imagine anywhere where there's a
tool integration, prompts, and evals,
you can go into design, you can go into
product, you can go to HR. It's just
basically workflow management in a
company.
Um and that's the thing where we think
it's going. Um
but if that's the case, then
you know, you're
just like people, you probably don't
want your engineers having access to
your finance systems, you don't want
your finance people having access to
your code base.
Like, you know, all of these things
you're going to need to set up policies
around. And even like regulatory
policies you're going to need that,
especially in a large public company.
Um so, you need layers to be able to
enforce that. AI's non-deterministic,
right? Like, it's like
you can't guarantee what the outcome is
based on any inputs.
If you're building a stable
infrastructure layer, you need it to be
deterministic. So, you need to put a
deterministic layer on top of this
non-deterministic technology.
It's the only way right now.
Okay, so it's it's almost like this
harness that will Yeah, control plane is
a great way to put it. Control plane for
the agents within maybe a corporate
Yeah. environment.
>> Centralize it. Like right now, like you
know, you you you see people using these
uh
AI agents. We had one customer that uh
you know, they
they have their developers running
agents on their laptops. They don't know
where they're running. This is one that
like blew through their token budget one
agent in 12 hours and they didn't know.
So, you centralize that. Okay, here's a
central runtime.
You you make it so agents can work
together in a secure way. So, you put
bubble wraps around them.
Um you don't want these agents just
yellowing it in your infrastructure,
right? So, like you have to put control
around them.
You know, I I I I I use this analogy.
Like there's this movie Gremlins. You
remember Gremlins?
Uh I haven't seen it, but Gremlins.
Yeah, it was like this cheesy Steel
Spielberg movie where these little furry
creatures started multiplying quick and
they just were causing chaos in town,
taking over the electric power grid.
Like AI agents are like that, right?
It's like they're just like once they
start multiplying and they're like you
can't predict what they're doing, like
that's a problem. So, you need to be
able to put a layer there to provide
some predictability and control around
that. That's what we're building.
Yeah, at this point, I feel like you
have so much management experience, so I
wanted to
uh discuss this high-level
uh management philosophy that I see in
the industry, which is that
um
I see that this Elon style Elon Musk
style of management is kind of like
getting in the details, micromanaging,
and I I hear a lot of people who are
against that as well and I'm curious
what side of that you're on and maybe we
can discuss the pros and cons of each of
the approaches.
Yeah, sure. Well, look, I think that
there's different tools for different
jobs. And so, what you're describing
when you talk about these two different
management styles, they're in two very
different environments. And so, I'm not
a micromanager, but I've also been
fortunate enough to have incredibly
capable people to work with.
So, you know,
you can think of an org as a top-down
org, like where you have a leader with a
very clear vision, and he's higher
you're hiring a workforce, he or she's
hiring a workforce to help achieve that
mission. Or, you know, you can be the
opposite of that and consider yourself
at the bottom of the org chart, and
you're trying to act as a tool to help
that team achieve their vision.
That's the one I am. Now,
that being said,
there are times where, you know, if your
team isn't performing, you know, and
I've worked
I've inherited some teams that were not
working well and things like that, where
I've had to go in and and micromanage.
But, not for long. You want to only use
it as a tool, in my opinion,
to to to fix things and then step back
out of that. I think that our our job in
in technology is a creative This is a
creative job, all right? Like, you you
don't know what it looks like often. You
just know what outcome you want, right?
And if you're going to do that, you have
to free people. You don't want to hire
smart people and think for them. You
want to just focus them on the outcomes.
You want to like clear their their their
what's blocking them. You want to be
able to probe and like ask great
questions and course correct them.
But, if you start mark micromanaging
really smart people,
you're going to lose them. Now, if you
look at some of these classic examples
that you mentioned like Elon and stuff
like that, think there was a lot of lot
of lost a lot of smart people that
weren't willing to work in that
environment. But, I didn't understand
the environment. Maybe it was necessary.
I can't speak to that.
I've built my career around hiring
really smart people, much smarter than
me, and getting out of their way and
just supporting them, you know,
trying to make them
give them the space to be the best that
they're at. And uh
So, I think
you know,
not saying there isn't room for this
micromanagement like get down into the
details. You need to do that every once
in a while, but like that's not If you
just that's your only mode of operation,
that's your only tool, it's only good
for a very specific thing.
When when you look back on your your
whole career, is there any career regret
that comes to mind that you think other
people could learn from?
Oh man. So, yeah, there's a lot
actually. And I wouldn't say they're
regrets because like I'm pretty happy
where I'm at and like everywhere led me
here. So, like you have to also look
back and go
I'm not going to punish myself over
mistakes if you're happy where you're
at. I'll tell you things though that
like I wish I would have known
uh or I wish I would have appreciated
when I was younger is like
I'm I'm not an intern age anymore. I'm a
little older and you know, time is my
scarce commodity now. Like so,
back when I was younger, it was okay to
like beat my head against the wall for
6-7 years. I'm like, I have all the time
in the world. I would like to have that
time back and spend it well. So, like be
sure you're doing what you love and be
sure you're having good days because
that's really your scarce commodity.
You know, so that's one thing.
Um
go where the smart people are. Like I
learned this by accident. Like I was
fortunate enough to get recruited into
Netscape and Borland, like where all the
smart people were.
Like going there really helped build me
a network that's just
you know, people that early engineers at
Netscape and Borland are kind of like
owning the valley now. Mark Andreessen
and you know, so so that that's also
good and that's where I got the best
mentors and learned the most.
And I'd say one simple tactical one if
you're just starting at a company, like
this might sound silly, but I would say
I wish I would have just maxed out my
401k on day one. Like just go max out
your 401k.
It sounds like like you're going to get
a reduction in salary and you may not be
starting out at high, but trust me,
you'll forget it. But like when you're
my age, that is going to be a giant
amount of money.
I wish I would have done that earlier.
So,
that's the other tactical thing I would
do.
If you could go back to the beginning of
your career and give yourself some
advice knowing everything you know now,
what would you say?
I would speak up more. Like you know, I
I remember thinking being afraid to
speak up because like I was worried that
people would think I was an idiot. Um,
but it turns out that like those are the
people now that I notice are the people
that even if what they say is off,
they're not afraid to speak up.
So, speak up. Like be curious. Like I
wish I would have networked more and and
asked people like more about what they
were doing.
And you know, one simple thing is like
it didn't occur to me is sort of a
version of go where the smart people or
like I was 7 years in Pennsylvania
working. That's where I'm from.
It didn't occur to me to like go to like
I got recruited into Borland, but like
in retrospect, it was like if I were an
actor and like it didn't occur to me in
7 years to go try Hollywood. It's like
you know,
it made all the difference was getting
into the valley where there was so much
opportunity and resources. I wish I
would have done that earlier.
That makes sense. Awesome. Well, thank
you so much for your time, James. I
really appreciate it. It was great to
meet you. Yeah, great. Thanks for taking
the time. It's been a fun conversation.
Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I've
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed and I
finally have a prototype. So, I'd love
to show you what we've built. It's
ultra-low profile and ergonomic and I
couldn't find anything like it on the
market. So, that's why we built it. I'll
put a link to the keyboard in the
description. You can take a look and
learn more about the project there. We
could definitely use your support. Also,
if you have any feedback for me about
the show, I'd love to hear it. Comments
on YouTube have led to guests coming on
like Ilya Grigoric and David Fowler. I
wasn't aware of them until someone
dropped a comment. Also, feedback in the
comments helped me learn to reduce the
number of cliffhangers in the intros.
So, your comments definitely make a
difference. Please keep letting me know
what you'd like to see more of in the
show and I'll see you in the next
episode.